Guide to the Charles Felton Scott Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Felton Scott papers
1889-1943
MS 779
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
(31 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, and papers on engineering. The largest portion concerns the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, of which Scott was an active member. Another large section is made up of Scott's administrative correspondence at Yale in the electrical engineering department (1911-1922). Also included are papers documenting Scott's employment at the Westinghouse Electrical and Manufacturing Company from 1888 to 1911 and includes correspondence, technical papers, and material for a biography of George Westinghouse. Pamphlets and other material issued by Engineers for Hoover (1928), and miscellaneous papers from the National Committee on Prisons and Prison Labor are also in the papers.
Scott, C.F. (Charles Felton), 1864-1944
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift to Yale University in 1945, and transfer from the School of Engineering.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Felton Scott Papers consist mainly of incoming and outgoing correspondence and some miscellaneous items, including engineering brochures, reports, and invitations to speak. Largely routine, the correspondence is composed of form letters, requests for evaluations of job applicants, and business letters.
The papers are arranged alphabetically by subject or author's name in one series spanning the years 1901 to 1923. Nearly one-third of the correspondence concerns the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, of which Scott was an active member. The remaining correspondence consists of the administrative files Scott maintained at Yale. Most of the letters dealing with the American Institute of Electrical Engineers are very routine, discussing the business aspects of the organization, minutes of meetings, and guest lecturers. The letters from the Yale files are again routine, dealing with instructors, student grades, new equipment for the department and the like. There is some mention of the reorganization of Yale University which occurred around 1920.
The Charles Felton Scott Papers provide little if any insight into Scott's importance as a scientist or an inventor. The papers may be of limited use to researchers interested in the formation and development of the electrical engineering department at Yale University in the early part of the twentieth century.
The papers were acquired by the Yale University Library in February 1945.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Felton Scott, born on September 19, 1864, in Athens, Ohio, was the son of William Henry and Sarah Felton Scott.
Scott received his B.A. degree from Ohio State University in 1885 and began graduate work in mathematics at Johns Hopkins University. While studying at Johns Hopkins, Scott taught mathematics and elementary science at the Baltimore and Ohio railroad apprentice school in Baltimore.
In 1887, having decided to pursue a career as an electrical engineer, Scott went to work for a construction company that was building an alternating current plant for the Baldwin Locomotive works in Philadelphia. In the summer of 1888, Scott began working at the Westinghouse Electric Company in Pittsburgh. At Westinghouse, Scott gained expertise in the application of the science of engineering to electrical problems and soon was recognized for his work on alternating currents.
Scott's first position at Westinghouse was as Nicholas Tesla's assistant. Tesla was the first person to develop a method of utilizing undulating current. Scott assisted Tesla in the development of a new inductor motor which used alternating current to transmit power. In 1890, Scott designed the first commercial polyphase alternating current motor. During this period, he was also involved in improving the transformers manufactured by Westinghouse. It was in this area that Scott made his best known technical contribution. In 1892, he designed the T-transformer, which could transform electric current from a two-phase system to a three-phase system. This transformer was used to develop the Niagara power project.
Scott welcomed the opportunity to show others the growing importance of electrical engineering. In the early part of the twentieth century, he turned from the practical application of his engineering skills to the challenge of imparting theoretical knowledge of electrical engineering to the generations which would apply electricity to all facets of their lives. As a step in this direction, he and others in the field felt it would be useful to have a single center for all existing engineering societies. In 1903, Scott took part in negotiations with Andrew Carnegie to plan the construction in New York City of a headquarters for all engineering societies in the United States. He also organized the Electric Club and founded a magazine for engineering students entitled Electric Journal.
Scott's interest in education deepened, and in 1911, he accepted a professorship in the new electrical engineering department of the Sheffield Scientific School of Yale University. Yale awarded Scott an honorary Master of Arts degree that same year. From 1911 to 1933, Scott taught in the electrical engineering department. During his tenure as chairman (1920-1933), the department expanded its reputation and acquired a separate building.
Scott was a member of most of the major engineering organizations in the United States and actively promoted the field whenever possible. From 1919 to 1920 he served on the committee that formulated plans for the Federated American Engineering Societies. He represented the American Institute of Electrical Engineers on the American Engineering Council from 1920 to 1933. Scott was president of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers from 1921 to 1923.
Charles Felton Scott retired from Yale University in 1933. He died on December 17, 1944.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Elections -- United States; Electrical engineering; Engineering; Educators; Engineers; Scott, C.F. (Charles Felton), 1864-1944; Westinghouse, George, 1846-1914; American Institute of Electrical Engineers; Westinghouse Electric Corporation; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Engineering; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School. Dept. of Electrical Engineering
- Original Accession, 1901-1923; 7.5; (18 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject or author's name.
  - A, 1911-1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Acme Wire Company, 1909-1917, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - American Association of Engineers, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1911-1923 (Box 1, Folder 10-16)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers
    - Committee on Development, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Committee on Education, 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Committee on Engineering Building, 1902-1905 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Committee on Industrial Power, 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Committee on the Library, 1901-1904 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - Committee on Lighting and Illumination, 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Committee on Meetings and Papers, 1921-1923 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Committee on Sections, 1914-1916, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
    - Committee on Standards, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Committee on Super-Power Systems, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Committee on Traction and Transportation, 1916-1918 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    - Committee on Transmission, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Connecticut section, 1921-1922, undated (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
    - "Engineer of the Twentieth Century", 1903 February-October (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
    - International Electrotechnical Commission, 1920-1922, undated (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    - Joint Conference Committee, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Lecture Hall record, 1913-1916 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Mailing lists, 1902-1904 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Membership lists, 1901-1902 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Presidential addresses, 1902 July-1903 (Box 3, Folder 45-46)
    - Proposal for Engineering Building, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Retiring president's address, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Student branches, 1903, 1915-1916 (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
    - Student branches, 1917-1918, 1921-1923 (Box 4, Folder 52-54)
    - Union Engineering Building, 1903 February- May 30, 1903 June-1904 Apr, undated (Box 4, Folder 55-66)
    - Yale branch, 1911, 1914-1921 (Box 5, Folder 67-71)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 1911-1917, 1919-1922 (Box 5, Folder 72-74)
  - B, 1911-1922 (Box 5, Folder 75-79)
  - Bozell, Harold V., 1918-1919, 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 80-82)
  - C, 1910-1923, undated (Box 6, Folder 83-90)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1911, 1914-1918, undated (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Central Station Meeting, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Century Electric Company, 1916-1919 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Chittenden, Russell H., 1911-1917, undated (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Class of 1911S (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Class of 1912S, 1912-1915 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Class of 1913S, 1912-1917 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Class of 1914S, 1912-1916 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Class of 1915S, 1913-1917 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Class of 1916S, 1914-1917 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Class of 1917S, 1915-1919 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Class of 1918S, 1917-1919 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Class of 1919S (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Class of 1920S, 1918-1919 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Class of 1921S, 1921, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Class of 1922S (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Class of 1923S, 1921-1922 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Clewell, Clarence E., 1914-1917 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Connecticut Company, 1913-1917 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Cooper Hewitt Electric Company, 1913-1917 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - D, 1911-1922 (Box 7, Folder 108-113)
  - E, 1911-1922 (Box 7, Folder 114-118)
  - Electric Journal, 1913-1922, 1911-1922 (Box 7, Folder 119-123)
  - Employment, 1915, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 124-125)
  - Engineering News, 1902-1903 (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Engineers' Society of Western Pennsylvania, 1916-1917 (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - F, 1913-1922 (Box 8, Folder 128-130)
  - Films, 1922, undated (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - Fire reports, 1914-1916 (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - G, 1911-1922, undated (Box 8, Folder 133-137)
  - General Electric Company, 1911-1921 (Box 8, Folder 138-142)
  - General Electric Review, 1912-1913 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Government correspondence, 1917 March-Dec, undated (Box 9, Folder 144-146)
  - Government recommendations, 1917-1918 (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - H, 1911-1918, undated, 1919-1922, undated (Box 9, Folder 148-152)
  - Hadley, Arthur T., 1919-1920 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Hartford Electric Light Company, 1911-1914 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - Herr, Edwin M., 1915 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - I, 1912-1918, 1921-1922 (Box 9, Folder 156-157)
  - University of Illinois, 1913-1917 (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Illuminating Engineering Society, 1914-1922 (Box 9, Folder 159-163)
  - J, 1912-1922 (Box 10, Folder 164-165)
  - Johns-Pratt Company, 1915-1917, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 166)
  - K, 1913-1922, undated (Box 10, Folder 167-169)
  - L, 1911-1922 (Box 10, Folder 170-174)
  - M, 1911-1918, undated, 1919-1922 (Box 10, Folder 175-180)
  - Macbeth-Evans Glass Company, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 181)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1911-1917 (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - Merchants' Association of New York, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 183)
  - N, 1911-1918, 1921-1922 (Box 11, Folder 184-185)
  - National Electric Light Association, 1914-1922, undated (Box 11, Folder 186-191)
  - Naval Consulting Board, 1916-1918 (Box 11, Folder 192)
  - Neostyle Company, 1916-1917 (Box 11, Folder 193)
  - New England Westinghouse Company, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 194)
  - O, 1916-1922 (Box 11, Folder 195-196)
  - P, 1911-1922, undated (Box 11, Folder 197-201)
  - Philadelphia Electric Company, 1916-1918 (Box 11, Folder 202)
  - R, 1913-1922 (Box 11, Folder 203-205)
  - Rice, C. B., [1911] (Box 12, Folder 206)
  - S, 1911-1923, undated (Box 12, Folder 207-215)
  - Sheffield Chemical Laboratory Committee, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 216)
  - Sheffield Scientific School, 1912-1917 (Box 12, Folder 217-220)
  - Sheffield Scientific School, 1918-1922 (Box 13, Folder 221-227)
  - Sheffield Scientific School
    - Applications for positions, 1913-1922 (Box 13, Folder 228-235)
    - Bulletin board notices, 1914-1918, undated, 1919-1922, undated (Box 14, Folder 236-239)
    - Course of studies, 1920-1922 (Box 14, Folder 240)
    - Directorship, 1921-1922 (Box 14, Folder 241)
    - Electrical Engineering Department, 1911-1916, 1921 January-Dec, undated (Box 14, Folder 242-246)
    - Electrical Engineering Departmental Meetings, 1920-1921 (Box 14, Folder 247)
    - Electrical engineering lecture notes, 1913-1916, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 248-249)
    - Engineers Club, 1913 (Box 14, Folder 250)
    - Examination schedules, 1921-1922 (Box 14, Folder 251)
    - Faculty parties, 1920-1924 (Box 15, Folder 252)
    - Graduate students, 1914-1915, 1919-1921, undated (Box 15, Folder 253-254)
    - Junior seminary papers, 1920-1921 (Box 15, Folder 255)
    - Mechanical Engineering Department, 1914-1922 (Box 15, Folder 256-259)
    - Office of the Dean, 1922 (Box 15, Folder 260)
    - Proposed visits, 1921-1922 (Box 15, Folder 261)
    - Registrar, 1921-1922 (Box 15, Folder 262)
    - Report on wiring, 1912 (Box 15, Folder 263)
    - Student Army Training Corps, 1911-1918 (Box 15, Folder 264)
    - Teaching positions, 1921-1922, undated (Box 15, Folder 265-266)
  - Sigma XI, 1921-1922, undated (Box 15, Folder 267)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1914-1918 (Box 15, Folder 268-270)
  - Southern New England Telephone Company, 1915 (Box 16, Folder 271)
  - Sterling Chemical Laboratory, 1923 (Box 16, Folder 272)
  - T, 1912-1920, 1922 (Box 16, Folder 273-274)
  - U, 1912-1922 (Box 16, Folder 275-276)
  - Unidentified fragments (Box 16, Folder 277)
  - United Electric Light and Water Company, 1914 (Box 16, Folder 278)
  - United States Fuel Administration, 1918 (Box 16, Folder 279)
  - V, 1914-1919, 1921-1922 (Box 16, Folder 280-281)
  - Visual Industrial Course, Inc., 1919-1920 (Box 16, Folder 282)
  - W, 1911-1922 (Box 16, Folder 283-289)
  - Western Electric Company, 1912-1918 (Box 16, Folder 290)
  - Western Electrical Instrument Company, 1914-1917 (Box 16, Folder 291)
  - Westinghouse Church Kerr and Company, 1911 (Box 17, Folder 292)
  - Westinghouse Club, 1914-1916 (Box 17, Folder 293)
  - Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company, 1911-1922 (Box 17, Folder 294-302)
  - Westinghouse Lamp Company, 1911-1917 (Box 18, Folder 303)
  - Westinghouse Memorial Committee, 1916-1918 (Box 18, Folder 304)
  - Westinghouse Yale Club, 1913-1915 (Box 18, Folder 305)
  - Woolsey Hall lighting, 1914-1915 (Box 18, Folder 306)
  - Yale Alumni Weekly, 1913-1916, 1919-1922 (Box 18, Folder 307)
  - Yale Co-operative Corporation, 1916-1917 (Box 18, Folder 308)
  - Yale Daily News, 1911-1923 (Box 18, Folder 309)
  - Yale Engineering Association, 1914-1917 (Box 18, Folder 310)
  - Yale Radio Broadcasting, 1922 (Box 18, Folder 311)
  - Yale University
    - Bureau of Appointments, 1919-1922 (Box 18, Folder 312)
    - Faculty, 1919-1920 (Box 18, Folder 313)
    - Graduate School, 1919-1922 (Box 18, Folder 314-316)
    - Honorary degrees, 1922 (Box 18, Folder 317)
    - Library, 1915-1918 (Box 18, Folder 318)
    - President's Office, 1916-1922 (Box 18, Folder 319)
    - Prudential Committee, 1920-1922 (Box 18, Folder 320)
    - Reorganization, 1919 (Box 18, Folder 321)
    - Salary increases, 1919 (Box 18, Folder 322)
    - Secretary's Office, 1914-1922, undated (Box 18, Folder 323-325)
    - Treasurer's Office, 1912-1922 (Box 18, Folder 326-327)
    - X, Y, Z, 1913-1922 (Box 18, Folder 328)
- Additional Material, Accession 1983-M-014
  This addition to the Charles Felton Scott Papers consists of correspondence, reports, engineering brochures and miscellaneous items identical to that contained in the original collection. The papers were in Yale University Archives School of Engineering records. Arranged alphabetically by subject or author's name, the papers are a supplement to the Charles Felton Scott Papers. There is no arrangement of the papers within the folders.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - American Engineering Council, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - American Engineering Council
      - Bulletins, 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - The Federated American Engineering Societies, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      - September meeting, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American Institute of Electrical Engineering
      - Secretary minutes, 1927-1932, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9-13)
      - Secretary minutes, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
      - General information, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Engineers for Hoover, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
    - Engineers for Hoover (Box 4, Folder 20-23)
      - Pamphlets, brochures, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Pamphlets, brochures (duplicates), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Replies to Hoover letters, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Signatures of committees, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - National Committee on Prisons and Prison Labor, 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
    - National Electric Lighting Association, 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 30-32)
    - National Electric Lighting Association
      - Inductive interference, 1920-1922 (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - "Question Box", 1904 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Technical Advisory Committee, 1920-1921 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Technical Advisory Committee, 1920-1923 (Box 6, Folder 36-38)
    - National Society for the Promotion of Industrial Education, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Personal Engineering Papers and Reports, 1894-1910 (Box 6, Folder 40-44)
    - Personal Engineering Papers and Reports, 1894-1910 (Box 7, Folder 45)
      - 1914-1921 (Box 7, Folder 46-50)
      - Reports and papers of colleagues, 1890-1905 (Box 7, Folder 51-52)
      - Reports and papers of colleagues, 1890-1905 (Box 8, Folder 53)
      - Cashing Papers, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 54)
      - Catalogues and brochures, undated (Box 9, Folder 55)
      - Photographs of power plants, undated (Box 9, Folder 56)
      - Printed material, 1905 (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Westinghouse Electrical and Manufacturing Company
      - 1889-1890, 1894-1898 (Box 9, Folder 58-63)
      - 1898-1906 (Box 10, Folder 64-73)
      - 1907-1911 (Box 11, Folder 74-79)
      - Biography of George Westinghouse, undated (Box 11, Folder 80)
      - Correspondence course, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 81)
      - Early history course, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 82)
      - The Electric Journal, 1907 (Box 11, Folder 83)
      - Frequency determination, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 84)
      - Impedence test on interworks road, 1905-1906 (Box 12, Folder 85)
      - Outline of experimental electricity, 1914 (Box 12, Folder 86)
      - Preparation of Westinghouse biography, 1919-1920 (Box 12, Folder 87-89)
      - Reactance capacitance, and transmission circuits, 1914 (Box 12, Folder 90)
      - Shop problems, 1912-1914 (Box 12, Folder 91)
      - Shop problems, 1912-1914 (Box 13, Folder 92)
      - The three circuits, 1914 (Box 13, Folder 93)
      - United Engineering Society (Box 13, Folder 94)